### Amélie Lehuen, Ph.D. - Estuarine ecosystems

3 rue de Vaucelles 14000 Caen 43 years old 06 72 18 94 51 alehuen@gmail.com







### 2020-23 - Doctoral thesis in Physiology and biology of organisms - populations - interactions

Caen University – ED497 nBISE – Laboratory of biology of organisms and aquatic ecosystems (BOREA) MNHN, CNRS 8067, SU, IRD 207, UCN, UA, Caen – Director: Dr. Francis Orvain

- Marine Ecosystem Engineers Long-Term Evolution ModelING in resPOnse to climate change and sediment Transport in Seine Estuary.
- Partners: IFREMER Brest; NIOZ Netherlands; Italian National Research Council, Italy; Cellule de Suivi du Littoral Normand; Maison de l'Estuaire.

### 2019-20 - MSc Ocean Sciences, Coastal Living Resources Exploitation - Caen University

- Coastal ecosystems and food webs, Coastal areas: Knowledge and sustainable management
- Physiology of marine organisms, Exploitation of fish, shellfish, and algal species

# 2018-19 - BSc Professions of environmental protection & management Ecological restoration & sustainable development - Caen University of Technology

- Natural habitats rehabilitation: Marine ecosystems management, Impact study, Ecological restoration, GIS; Habitats analysis;
   Sustainable Development and Environmental Management.
- Tutored project: Primary production analysis of microphytobenthos on the Orne estuary foreshore and spectral data acquired by GIS.

### 2004 - Engineer degree - Rouen National Institute of Applied Sciences (INSA)

Fine Chemistry and Engineering Department – specialism in Materials and Polymers

### 2024-25 (15months) - Post-Doc - fixed-term contract - Caen University

EValuation of the ecological functioning of lateral mudflats upstream of Tancarville to guide new ecological restoration projects through a comparative approach to the functional biodiversity of benthic communities (EVEREST).

### 2023-24 (3months) - Researcher Engineer - fixed-term contract - Caen University

Marine Ecosystem Engineers Long-Term Evolution ModelING in resPOnse to climate change and sediment Transport in Seine Estuary (MELTING POTES).

### 2020-23 (3 years) – PhD Researcher – Caen University

Marine Ecosystem Engineers Long-Term Evolution ModelING in resPOnse to climate change and sediment Transport in Seine Estuary (MELTING POTES).

### 2020-22 (46h) - Vacation teaching IUT Grand Ouest Normandie Caen campus 2

2021-22 - L3: Tutored project

2020-21 - L2: Applied computer data analysis, Environmental analysis; L3: Marine ecosystem management & marine biology, Tutored project

# 2020 (9 months) – Research engineer – internship and fixed-term contract – Laboratory of biology of aquatic organisms and ecosystems (BOREA) MNHN, CNRS 8067, SU, IRD 207, UCN, UA, Caen

Prediction of the distribution of macrozoobenthic species in the Seine estuary in response to hydro-morphosedimentary changes: first applications on the population of cockles, *Cerastoderma edule*. Definition of optimal ecological niches by quantile regression.

#### 2019 (6 months) – Benthic technician – internship – GEMEL-Normandie – Luc sur Mer

Evaluation of a stock of bivalves and associated fauna following a scientific reserve creation on the west coast of Cotentin.





Organization - management

Full project management Schedule building and monitoring Budget definition and control Leading a multidisciplinary team

# Education

Professional experience

### Amélie Lehuen, Ph.D. - Estuarine ecosystems

3 rue de Vaucelles 14000 Caen 43 years old 06 72 18 94 51 alehuen@gmail.com









**Lehuen, A.** and Orvain, F. (2024) A cockle-induced bioturbation model and its impact on sediment erodibility: A meta-analysis, Science of The Total Environment, 912, p. 168936. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.168936.

**Lehuen, A.**, Dancie, C., Grasso, F., et al., 2023. A quantile regression approach to define optimal ecological niche (habitat suitability) of cockle populations (*Cerastoderma edule*). https://normandie-univ.hal.science/hal-04438267.

**Lehuen A.**, Oulhen R.M., Zhou Z., de Smit J., Cozzoli F., Bouma T., Orvain Francis, 2023. Multispecies macrozoobenthic seasonal bioturbation effect on sediment erodibility. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seares.2024.102525.



August 2022 - Nereis park – Logonna-Daoulas, France

**Lehuen, A.**, Dancie, C., Grasso, F., et al., 2022. A modelling approach for predicting species distribution in Seine estuary by applying an Optimal Ecological Niche model: First application to *Cerastoderma edule* population.

**Lehuen, A.** et Orvain, F., 2022. Bioturbation model of *Cerastoderma edule* based on metabolic activity and sediment composition: a meta-analysis.

**Lehuen, A.** et Orvain, F., 2022. MELTING POTES Marine Ecosystem Engineers Long-Term Evolution: A ModelING study of benthic faunal activity and distribution in resPOnse to climate change and sediment Transport in Seine Estuary.

September 2022 - ECSA59 - San Sebastian, Spain

**Lehuen, A.**, Dancie, C., Grasso, F., et al., 2022. A modelling approach for predicting species distribution in Seine estuary by applying an Optimal Ecological Niche model: First application to *Cerastoderma edule* population.

# Expertise

Mai 2023 (4 days) - NEO workshop - ILICO - Caen

Study of "Optimal Ecological Niche" species distribution models and inter-SNO (Systèmes National d'Observation) taxonomic and functional distribution: Coupling of hydro-biological data (low-frequency SOMLIT and high-frequency COASTHF) with planktonic (PHYTOBS) and benthic (BENTHOS) species distribution data in coastal ecosystems of mainland France. Workshop for 15 people.

### 2024 (ongoing) Member of Conseil Scientifique de l'Estuaire de la Seine (CSES) – DREAL Normandie

The Council issues opinions on development programmes, works or management measures likely to have an impact on the functioning of estuarine ecosystems.

2023 (ongoing) Member of CYBER-COAST group - Future Earth Coasts (FEC)

International working group on the resilience of ecosystems in the face of global change, from the perspective of cybernetics and eco-energetics.

2021 (ongoing) Association Treasurer <u>GEMEL</u> Normandie

Finances: Cash flow monitoring, budget forecasts, annual balance sheet. Implementation of cost accounting. Discussions with chartered accountant and statutory auditor.

Social management: 3 permanent employees (contract reviews, individual interviews), recruitment of temporary contracts.

Association: Set up of a Local Aid Scheme (DLA), development of organizational tools and practices to monitor projects, workload, costs, and volunteer activities.

ey words

Responsibly

Bioturbation Macrozoobenthos Estuary, Coastal Intertidal, Mudflat Species Distribution Model (SDM)
Optimal Ecological Niches
Quantile regression
Suitability index

Erosion model Hydro-morpho-sedimentary model Metabolic rate Data analysis

Geo-statistics

### Amélie Lehuen, Ph.D. - Estuarine ecosystems

3 rue de Vaucelles 14000 Caen 43 years old 06 72 18 94 51 alehuen@gmail.com







### 2018 (8 months) – QHSE engineer – GB Ouest – Revima-APU Project – Caudebec en Caux

Creation of chemicals database, collective and individual protections rationalization, study of REACH exposure scenarios.

### 2011-17 (6 years) – Utilities Project Manager – GB Ouest –Chevron Oronite Project – Le Havre

Quantitative and qualitative improvement of the condensate network, sharing of KPIs and Best Practices.

Replacement of a steam boiler (€4.3m), improving the reliability of steam distribution, optimising the demineralisation unit.

Consolidation of the cooling water network (performance and energy savings).

Bringing the thermal fluid network up to standard and eliminating risks. Study and thermal assessment of the network.

Overall plan €1.5m/year, ~15 projects, development and sharing of project management tools.

Coordination with the General Services shutdown unit for work on the networks (every 18 months).

### 2010-11 (6 months) – Process Improvement engineer – Lubrizol – Rouen

Health, Safety and Environment project management, global budget 1M€.

### 2010 (8 months) - Environment engineer - Petroplus - Petit Couronne Refinery

Pilot odour treatment of the WWTP decanter: installation, sampling and analysis in coordination with the supplier. Monitoring and improvement of flow and performance of the refinery Waste Water Treatment Plant. Communication of indicators.

### 2007-09 (1,5 year) – Process Control engineer – Lubrizol – Rouen

Development of an online statistical analysis and quality control module, interface between US (Emerson Process Management) developers/statisticians and production to obtain a process-oriented tool.

Development of statistical process control tools on Statgraphics to detect process drifts, alarm dashboard, Six Sigma development context.

### 2007 (5 months) – R&D Process engineer – Cristal-Millennium Inorganic Chemicals – Le Havre

Stabilization and optimization of the white gypsum unit, industrial tests, US communication.

### 2004-05 (2 years) – Process Improvement engineer – Lubrizol – Rouen

Modelling of mixing tank washings with experimental design and process optimisation to reduce the quantity of oil, inter-batch times and contamination between batches.

Continuous improvement projects: new stirring systems, installation of a drum emptying system, etc. Production support and project management. Analysis of non-conformities.

#### Permaculture

2019: Permaculture Design Course – CDFP l'Escargotier, Le Havre

#### Music

2017 & 19: Jazz singing masterclass – Jazzitudes, Lisieux

10 years of musical practice in band as singer and guitarist

2012-17: Monthly open mike: Lavomatic Tour

Dance

2004-12: Mandingue and Sabar weekly practice – Kaï Danse, Rouen 2012-14: Contemporary dance shows – Le Phare, Le Havre

lerests

Previous experience: 14 years